Today we are going to talk about Exploring
Real Market Needs.
And I want to emphasis the term real here
and
that often times that have students that
have an idea they
came up with they dreamt about it, they
thought about it
in the shower it just was a kind of an
Piffany.
But it may not be a real need and so with
that we are going to look at today.
Is how you begin to try and segment the
things that are real market
needs from the things that might be novel
ideas but perhaps there's not a
market opportunity for it.
Specifically, when we look at building a
successful company.
We want to introduce a product or service
that, satisfies
customer needs or wants in a better way
than competitors.
And again, we'll use the terms needs and
wants somewhat interchangeably.
Many of us buy more of what we want versus
what we need.
But there's also a lot of interchange
within that.
so in that way again, when we talk about
needs and wants we're kind of combing in
the terms and using them synonymously.
The other piece of the equation when we
determine what to buy is that of price.
And it's not necessarily the cheapest
price, it's not necessarily the highest
price.
But it's a price that the company has set
that's something that makes sense for its
business model and the value proposition
for it's
customers and it's needs and wants that
they're fulfilling.
So in that way
when we being to think about real market
needs, we're going to look at
both sides of this of both the need or the
want of the customer.
But as well as how do you price things
appropriately.
So in that way when we think about
understanding needs
it's a question of is there a problem
that's unsolved.
And we've talked about this company square
space,
[SOUND]
that has the hundred employees that is
valued at over $100 million.
And it came with, again, a computer
science student being
unhappy with the existing web publishing
tools that were out there.
And he built something, not with the
intent of starting
a company, he built something to help him
build websites easy.
He had some ideas and some thoughts on
creating
multiple websites.
He didn't want to do them all from
scratch.
So he started building a series of tools
that he could use.
He showed it to his friend.
Friend said, that's pretty cool.
I'll pay you $500 for that.
What did he think then?
There might be other people that I can
sell this to.
And so in that way I can solve his own
problem.
Google, same thing, they did not sit down
intending to start a company.
They didn't write a business plan
They were students doing research, wanted
to have a more effective search
technology,
built that for themselves.
Friends started using it, classmates
started using it, campus started using it,
and then later, the thought was, we could
build a business on this.
So again, solving your own problem can
often be a starting point.
And again, thinking about a better way.
And there is some industries that, again,
had not evolved for a long time.
The rental car market had not evolved for
a long time.
Until the zip cars and, again, these other
aspects of being able to have a
distributed
easy pick up drop off, low price, rent by
the hour, instead of rent by the day.
If you need to go to the grocery store,
you probably don't want to pay 24
hours of rental car pricing to do that.
You might want to pay and hour or two and
that's what zip car does, you pay by the
hour.
And again pricing and we again use the
word better pricing.
And not necessarily lower pricing.
Few of us will go into a store and say,
I'm going
to buy the cheapest shampoo, the cheapest
milk and the cheapest underwear.
We're looking at pricing.
We might not necessarily go in and say,
oh,
I'm just going to buy the most expensive
of everything.
But we think about what
do I like,
perhaps ingredients, we pay attention to
the branding.
Do we like the colors?
Do we like the shape?
Do we like the feature and the function?
And that influence is our decision, so
price influences but its all undo you'd
necessarily decide on the cheapest.
So how do you see these needs and how to
do you recognize that and, and again its
important to recognize
that being a little bit better is a start
up probably isn't enough, why is that the
case?
If you like a brand, if you like a
product, if
you like a piece of apparel, if you like a
certain beverage.
What would make you switch?
What would make you switch away?
>> Something that's, else is a similar,
a similar product.
>> Okay.
>> Getting better and it's, has better
[INAUDIBLE]
>> Okay.
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
>> So there's something that's, you
know, an improvement,
and a noticeable improvement over what you
already have.
Typically if you are happy with what you
already have it's going to take something
to really get you over the edge and they
get you transition out of that.
But if its something you've never had
before
[SOUND]
and this is where, again, what we're
talking about with first mover advantages.
If it's something you've never had before,
or if it's a new
problem that you've identified, you don't
have to steal your competitors customers.
Everybody's looking for something to enter
into the, a part of.
So, oftentimes in trying to get a feel for
what's a real need, we look for problems.
We don't necessarily ask somebody, would
you like a product that did this?
You're trying to get a sense of
[UNKNOWN]
for existing products or existing problems
that are
out there, where you are having some
issues.
So, there is a department on
campus, called The Fischell Department of
Bioengineering.
There is a person named Robert Fischell.
He is an inventor.
Predominately in biomedical and medical
devices.
And he goes to doctors, he goes to
hospitals,
he goes to ER's, he ask doctor's what's
your problem?
Why does he do that?
>> See how he can help them?
>> See how he can help.
What procedures are you doing that you
don't have the right equipment?
What types of measurements are you trying
to do that you're not
getting a lot of accuracy, or a lot of
reliability, in those measurements?
Are there things that you do on a regular
basis that are awkward?
And I'm going to go home and invent
something for you.
And he has, I think, upwards of 300
patents.
So far he's contributed $31 million to the
university.
What's that tell you when someone can
donate $31 million?
>>
[UNKNOWN]
[CROSSTALK]
>> They have at least 31, and probably a
fair amount more than that.
He builds nothing.
He manufactures nothing.
He sells no product.
How do you get wealthy by doing that?
>> He comes up with the idea and sells
the idea.
>> He sent, essentially licenses the
concepts.
Doesn't necessarily license the idea, but
licenses the invention.
So if you're going to have a heart
[SOUND]
stint, something that's going to be
implanted in
your heart, and it's going to hold open,
channels for blood to flow in.
Why might you want to license that?
Two large companies that are in that
business versus going at it on your own.
>> The large companies, I mean, they
probably have
more money, more resources to start a
business, I mean.
>> They have the tens of millions of
dollars that it takes.
To go through and do the research, to do
the clinical trials, to work with the FDA,
to roll that out, to commercialize it.
And if you were in the business
of looking for a heart stent, are you
going to buy Bob's Heart Stents?
So there's a branding element there as
well, you
tend to buy from the companies that you
know.
And he's done it again, fundamentally, by
going
in and talking to doctors about what they
need.
And keeps delivering solutions to them.
So what we can do in a fairly efficient
way,
as we have ideas, you can talk with
customers directly.
But what you see here is if you go to
Amazon, search
on any product that you wish, then you'll
see some level of returns.
So for this I searched on iPhone 5 speaker
docks, and I get upwards of 9,000 results.
And with these and again, if you've
searched on Amazon before you know that
you can go, you can search, you can find,
you can search by category.
You can read about the product, you can
see a picture, you can see a price.
What else do you see?
>> How the reviews of the product.
>> You see reviews of the product.
And in this scenario for this first
product I have 192 reviews.
For the second product I have 1,305.
For the third product
I have 366.
So add those up and you're
approaching 2,000 reviews of people that
bought,
own and have used these iPhone 5 speaker
docks.
How else would I get 2,000 people to tell
me what they like and what they
dislike about an iPhone 5 speaker doc.
If I don't do this,
what else can I do?
>> You can ask them.
>> Who is them?
>> Customers of iPhone 5.
>> How do you find them?
>> You go to the store.
>> You go to the store?
>> Yeah.
>> So Best Buy,
[CROSSTALK]
they're going to let you post up shop?
>> Yeah.
>> No.
>>
[UNKNOWN]
[LAUGH].
>> So again can't,
[COUGH]
with any degree of scale or reliability,
go to retailers.
They're not going to tell you information
about their customers.
And customers probably aren't going to
take the time to talk to you.
>> I say, go to the discussion
boards online the Apple discussion boards
where they.
>> OK.
You could do something similar.
So, you could go to the retailers and see
how consumers have rated products.
Or, you could to the enthusiest sites, the
Apple discussion boards.
So, again, another platform.
I've let you go online and find people
talking about these products.
>> You could establish a customer
service line.
>> Say again.
>> Establish a customer service line.
>> OK.
How does that work?
>> well customers would call the phone
line
for any complaints they have about the
product.
>> OK.
How were they going to get your
information to call you and
how were you going to resolve their
problem?
>> Well, you could post the number
online, something like a website.
>> Post the number online.
So take a step back again.
You have an idea for entering this market.
So you're not in the market yet.
You're trying to figure out if I were to
enter this market and design an
iPhone 5 speaker dock, what should be
the features, the functions, the price
point, etc.
So again, you're at
a point that you're not equipped to solve
problems.
You haven't sold any product yet.
You're simply just trying to understand.
What do people like and dislike about the
products?
>> Like when they have to register it
like for a
warranty or something like that having to
fill out a survey.
>> But you're jumping ahead of it.
So and, what I mean by this is that for
Logitech, the middle brand here, or for
Bose you're both right.
If I'm Logitech I should have a customer
service line to resolve complaints.
If I'm Logitech, I should have a product
warranty registration system.
But I'm saying, if you want to compete
against Logitech, if want to compete
against Bose,
how do you get customers to tell you
how they feel about your competitors
products and services?
>> Telemarketing.
How do you find people that are owners of
these products?
>> Just randomly call people?
I don't know
[LAUGH].
>> Randomly call people.
How many people here have an iPhone 5
speaker dock?
>> I have one.
>> So, perhaps three.
So for every thousand phone calls we make,
we find 10% of the people even have it.
Somebody calls you and wants to talk to
you about
your iPhone 5 speaker dock, are you
going to talk to them?
>> No.
>> Then of the
[CROSSTALK]
10% that answered the phone, none of them
are going to talk to us.
>>
[LAUGH]
[UNKNOWN]
>> And there's an expense
[COUGH].
It costs money to do that.
This free, aside from you time.
What else do we do when we go out and are
considering a higher item purchase?
If your going to spend a couple
hundred dollars on something, particularly
electronics.
What do you typically do?
>> Get cheaper better alternatives.
>> But how do you decide which ones you
want to buy?
>> You go to the store and try it first.
>> You go to the store and try it out.
What else should you do?
>> Ask
your friends.
>> Ask friends.
What else?
>> Reviews.
>> You look for reviews.
And so in that way not only might you look
at consumer reviews, but you look at the
expert reviews.
You look at the reviews that are written
by the magazines that
cover automotives or electronics or
refrigerators
or whatever it is that you're considering.
But again, the expert reviews give you
some perspective
that I'd rather have 2,000 people tell me
their experience as a user over time.
One fault with a lot of the expert reviews
is they're reviewing the new product.
They don't necessarily review the product
after it's
been used for six months or a year.
So in that way, again, very valuable to go
in and do this type
of thing when you can through and find
people that are owners, that are users,
that do it relatively real time, en mass.
And you have a big volume of content here.
That you're able to work with, and you can
go in too, and
read these individual reviews, and you can
see most helpful or favorable reviews.
You would read the critical reviews, you
could see some scale
of how many people really liked it, how
many people didn't like.
And you can get a lot of good information
this way on
the cheap and relatively fast.
You don't have to build a survey, you
don't have to
worry about how do I find people that own
these products.
And if I find them how do I incentivize
them to respond
you simply go and, and see what do people
like, and don't like.
What's the problem with doing your
research this way, and only this way?
>> You
have a biased set of people.
>> You may have a biased set of people.
And some people criticize Yelp, and some
of these other platforms,
[INAUDIBLE]
if I'm a restaurant owner.
Am I just going to go in once a day, and
give my restaurant a five star rating?
>> yeah.
>> And, that's difficult to manage.
So there might be some element of fraud
invovled with it, to be mindful of.
Any other problems with this?
>> Yep.
If you had a faulty product that didn't
work.
You don't know necessarily that
representativeness of what they're saying.
That they did a product when they pulled
them out the mailbox, they dropped it.
And then when they took it in their home,
and opened it up, it was broken.
So, again, there's some element of
it being somewhat of an uncontrolled
environment.
Yep.
>>
[UNKNOWN]
reviews like you have
[SOUND]
different views on it, so its like
inconsistent.
>> Okay.
>>
[UNKNOWN]
>> There's some level of inconsistency.
in this model, we see out of 1300, its at
about 4 1/2 stars on a 5 star scale.
So we see some measure of consistency, and
we see kind of an even curve.
Where there are 50 and 30 and 70 people
that really didn't like it but
300 and 800 that do so you want to look at
all of the above.
You want to get some sense
of, for the ones that like, what themes
are central
and I might want to incorporate those
elements into my design.
And for the ones that don't like, are
there things there,
that I can recognize and perhaps solve or
resolve in your design?
>> I was just going to say the, this
market is only showing people who first of
all have using the Internet and are also
willing to go back and review it.
>> Okay.
>> They're going to get less people.
>> So
what's a smaller population of it's people
that are taking the time to do.
And you tend to see people that are
doing this type of commenting on the outer
bounds.
People that are really happy, take the
time to make comment.
People that are very dissatisfied, take
the time to make comment.
If you bought it, then it's okay and it
does what you thought it would.
You probably, on average not going to take
the time to review.
So, again, it's some
of those survey
[UNKNOWN]
to think about.
But in the absence of what your other
options are, of I'm
not exactly sure how you would affordably
fined owners, particularly 2000 owners.
To get 2,000 pieces of feedback on an
iPhone 5 speaker dock.
If not to do things like this.
So, helpful in understanding market,
understand the need.
So, again, all that factors into being
able to
think about, I've got an idea, I've got a
concept.
Let me go out do a little bit of research,
see
what consumers think about it and so
that's our starting point.
And from there it's an element of well
what can I do?
How do I build?
How do I develop?
What do I do about it?
And what's the future of that and how are
things involving?
And in that platform it gives you the
opportunity to go out
and do a bit more further
research together information about
customer preferences.
>>
[COUGH]
>> And at that stage you can think about
the element of groups and surveys and
focus groups.
Anybody been in a focus group?
You know what I mean by focus group?
And what's a focus group?
>> A focus group is a bunch of people
who
are selected by a company who wants to do
product testing.
>> Okay.
What's a bunch?
>> people who they believe.
>> What's a number?
>> it can be anywhere from like six to,
I'd say, even 100.
>> Okay.
Tends to be relatively small groups.
So single digits, maybe a few dozen
people.
But the orientation of let's put people in
a room as
a group, and talk to them about their
experiences likes, dislikes, etc.
And the idea there it's a bit more
informal, you began to see
where people are feeding off one another
side.
There was contributed in the things.
Different than an interview which is
typically a one to one
and interview different than a survey is
surveys are often written.
And with those surveys typically they are
objective, and that you're checking
the box, you're agreeing, you're
disagreeing,
you're rating things on a scale.
Interviews, a little more open-ended.
You can respond, you can inquire, you can
ask
why, and what, and how, in a different
way.
And so all of those are things you can do
to get some sense of what they've done,
what they're doing.
And what are they thinking about you?
And in that way it helps to either
validate that the idea
that you have is indeed a good idea, and a
marketable idea perhaps.
Versus something that might have been an
interesting concept,
but there might not be a market for it.
At least in its current conception.
When you go through and think about where
how do I find data.
How do I find Market Research.
And there are endless resources for that.
this is part of list of tools that Steve
Blank who is active in
the entrepreneurship education spaces
identified.
And these are a few that I would start
with that gives you some sense of
broadly research on public companies, how
large are
markets, how many dollars are spent in
certain
industries, geographies, things of that
nature.
>>
[COUGH]
>> You can learn about website traffic
and populations and tranges and growth.
From there you can go through and look at
specific business statistics, so
there are different sets of databases that
are geared toward things, like census.
What's the census?
>> When the, when a government counts up
how many people
that there are in a population.
>> Okay.
>> Area.
>> So, census looks and things like
population
by area, by geography by zip code by age.
>> Yeah.
Now.
It just, I mean.
Look it has a bunch of stats of the nation
as a whole and different ethnicities.
>> Okay.
>> So.
>> So they're looking at gender.
They're looking at education.
So a host of different stats.
Why does that matter?
Why might you for a given zip code want to
know about the people there?
>>
[COUGH]
it's so you can target a certain group of
people like elders.
>> Okay.
So if you're considering serving a certain
market, either locating operations there.
Or selling your product there.
Or investing your money in marketing
dollars there.
You want to know well, who is there?
And who are they?
This is a central way that restaurants
decide where to locate, this is
the central way that they decide where do
we
build malls, where are we going to locate
new apartment buildings?
It's, what's the population that's there?
How has it changed?
And then doing some analysis and thinking
about, how is it going to change?
there's also data that load side venture
capital the PwC MoneyTree is a big one.
And with that you can see for free, and
all of these are free resources,
you can see.
Where are venture capitalists putting
their money?
What types of industries?
What geographies?
How many companies did they invest in?
What was the stage of those companies?
How much did they invest on average per
company, per industry, per region?
And so in that way, it gives you some
sense of what's going on in the market
space.
Lot's of other.
Resources that are there and all these are
links
that you can go back to for later.
so with all of these links, you can go in
and see things on a national level,
an an international level, of being able
to
capture and understand what's going on in
these markets.
So, again, pages and pages of links.
That you can use based on what it is
you're trying to do, where
you're trying to do it but there's no
shortage of market data out there.
In many cases
governments and states are investing in
measuring this.
Why do they do that?
Why does the county or state, put dozens
or hundreds of people to work collecting
data
[SOUND]
on this type of thing.
>> I mean, I know, at least for some
people, at least my
[INAUDIBLE]
that he looks for the stats more to that's
[UNKNOWN]
case community.
>> Okay.
So there's an element of when it comes to
things like federal aid programs.
When it comes to things like economic
development.
When it comes to attracting businesses
they want to
have a good representation of here's who
we are.
And here's why we would be a good fit for
what it is that they're trying to attract.
>>
[SOUND]
well, ultimately it'll benefit them like
economically and
financially because if they because if
they give
the data then they'll track certain
businesses into
that state so they would get, and with
taxes.
>> Yep.
So if you, you can say here is the income
profile of our folks, here's the education
profile of our folks.
Here's a number of people that we have.
Here's a number of perhaps young people
that we
have, if that's a market that people are
targeting.
So in that way,
they spend a lot of time doing that, and
they make it publically available.
Again, available to you as well, to be
able to
go through and see what's going on in the
market.
So with that you can do a lot of things,
you can have a lot
of idea, you can go through and you can
recognize that there are market needs.
You can do some research and validate
those needs but,
then there is a question of what do I do?
I have my iPhone 5 speaker dock idea.
And I've gone through, and I have 30
things, that people want.
If I ask you if you like something, you
may say
yes, if I tell you what it costs, your
mind may change.
So it gives you the opportunity to say, do
you like this set
of futures for this price, or this set of
futures for this price?
And again, you're doing this all before
you have manufactured
a thing.
You're doing this all before you have
prototyped anything.
You're still in the process of trying to
understand what is that is that we should
desire.
And what products and services make sense
for
the market that we're trying to compete
in.
And in that way that's what we
mean by this separation and ranking of
preferences.
And that it gives you some sense of what
exactly do you want to do.
So in summary when you're beginning to
think
about entrepreneurial ideas, we want to
recognize and
try to seek those real needs and wants.
And we also want to recognize the role
that price plays,
as we consider what we might want to bring
to the market.
The way that we do that is first to
research creatively.
So you may not necessarily have the time
or budget to do elaborate market research.
But through some of the tools and
techniques that we've talked about today,
it gives you some insights on what you can
do with reasonable accuracy,
fairly quickly and fairly affordably.
What you're also going to need to do is
use some of your own intuition.
So in that way if you're truly doing
something
innovative by definition it should be a
bit new.
And maybe there are competitors out there
now
or in the past that you can learn from.
But at the end of the day you're probably
going to be trying to bring
some things to market that you're not
going to find perfect market research to
align with.
And so, you're applying some of your own
experiences, you're applying some of your
own background, you're
[UNKNOWN]
applying some of your own know-how and
analysis to evaluate the research that
you're finding.
And then lastly, and arguably the most
importantly,
is to think about market segments and
niches.
And we'll talk about this a little bit
later but find a mine way
[UNKNOWN]
think about is the specific market.
And now our market that you've
[UNKNOWN]
serve, that you can
brand there, that you can
[UNKNOWN]
our customer and that you can build your
skills and abilities and capabilities.
So
[UNKNOWN]
in bigger markets later but it gives you a
foothold.
And, it gives you an entryway into
entering a market and you can
even specialize within that, and a better
way than many of the existing competitors.