As we explore business plan, there's also
the question of
figuring out what's the best way to offer
the plan?
What should it include, what level of
detail?
And so there are a variety of these
types of questions that we'll address in
today's lecture.
First of all, it's important to recognize
that there's no single right format.
The formats do vary.
And although business plans and investor
presentations tend to cover very similar
topics,
it really depends on the audience that you
are developing the plan for.
If it's for an internal audience, then I
can share some examples for you today.
And these are great examples one is from
the small
business association and one is from a
leading venture capital
firm in the U.S. And either of these
models will
work for you and your internal team within
your organization.
If you are writing a plan that's going to
be submitted for grant funding,
for loan, for lending, for investors, I
would certainly
council you to see what their preferred
format is.
Or you might just be changing sections
around, you
might be adding a little more detail than
others.
Or there might be specific things that you
would
include within an appendix, that they will
be looking for.
so in that way again, I would say that
many
plans covers some more content but always
check in and
make sure that you're writing the plan and
covering the
content for the audience that you're
going to be submitting it to.
So while there's not a single format, I'm
going to share two of them today.
One is from the US small business
administration.
And so this is essentially, the table of
contents for what
they look for, when they're working with
entrepreneurs to write plans.
Typically starts with an executive
summary, then
some discussion of the company and the
product.
You'll talk about the market,
the competition, the customers, the
industry, all in part three.
Part four is largely about the team, how
you're going to organize and operate.
Five is sales and marketing, advertising
inclusive.
Six, you get into some more details about
future categories and product lines.
And then the final elements are the
funding and the financials.
So we'll look at each
of these briefly.
So executive summary, if you're working on
nominally a
20 page plan, executive summary might be
two pages.
[NOISE]
It also, should be a summary and not
an introduction, and people often get this
confused.
What does an introduction do?
When you read an introduction to a paper,
or an introduction to a book?
>> It leads you into the main idea.
>> It leads you into it.
It kind of gives you a little bit of a
background, gives you a little warm up.
What happens when you read the
introduction?
Can you not read the rest of the plan or
not read the rest of the book and know
what happens?
No, you have been introduced.
Conversely what should a summary do?
What should a summary do?
>> well it should, tell you everything
that
you need to know, but state it very small.
>> Okay, it should do, and as
prescribed, it should summarize, it should
tell you
everything that's critical, but do it in a
very abbreviated way.
So within your executive summary, it
should have the highlights
of the whole plan, but in a page or two.
>> Is this all on the SBA's website?
>> it's on the SBA site, yep, and it'll
be posted on our site as well.
>> Okay.
>> so in that way, what you see here, is
that with the executive
summaries, it's the whole, plan
summarized.
Why write such a thing, if you give
somebody
a plan, expecting them to read the whole
plan?
>> You can make a good first impression.
>> Okay.
Can make a good first impression.
What do investors do with executive
summaries as related to the plan?
>>
[COUGH].
>> What do you think they use the
executive summary to figure out?
>> Whether it's worth even meeting the
rest of
[CROSSTALK]?
>> Am I going to even read your plan?
The popular venture capital firms get 100
plans a day.
The really popular ones get 500 plans a
day.
And these are companies that might only be
ten or 20 person companies.
So venture capital firms while they manage
a lot of money, are often relatively
small, dozens of employees if that, who's
going to read 100 plans a day?
So in that way with the executive
summaries, it is essentially your
opportunity to make
an impression to try and persuade people
to go and read the rest of the plan.
So with that, when you begin to get into
the plan, so the executive summary lays on
top.
From there the next section is the company
description in the context of who are you?
What do you do?
How do you do it?
And when we look at what's the difference
between a
business plan and an investor
presentation, the content is similar.
So this is the content that you would use,
the
order that we're going through here, for
an investor presentation.
You're just typically doing it in
PowerPoint as
opposed to doing it in a Word document.
So, with company description, you begin to
introduce the
firm, you begin to introduce what you do,
you
begin to highlight the success factors,
how long have
you been around, what have you
accomplished to date.
When you get into talking about market in
the SBA's
format, they include a lot of things in
this section.
Within the market analysis, they begin to
talk about
the industry, talk about the life cycle
and growth rates
and stages so again, all of the pieces of
industry analysis that you would expect,
would be covered here.
They talk about the competition, strengths
and weaknesses, entry barriers,
and they talk about the regulatory
environment,
and they talk about the customers in that
space;
demographics, psychographic, locations,
behaviors,
buying decisions and patterns, etc.
When we look at the organizations piece,
this is
where you begin to introduce the people of
the company.
Who are you?
What have you done?
What do you want to do?
Do you have advisers?
Do you have directors?
So, you will cover all of that as well.
Within the marketing plan, so here we've
gone beyond talking about the market of
the
customers and gone into specifically, of
how
are we going to market this product, or
service?
Where are we going to advertise?
How much are we going to spend on
advertising?
What's kind of the branding, and
positioning that we want to have?
How are we going to sell it?
Are we selling it directly to customers,
are we
doing it face to face, online through
partners, we're going
to wholesale to retailers, that are then
going to
sell, through various cost and pricings
and logic for that.
Talking about benefits of the product or
service.
Also it's rare that you have a one product
company.
Most companies may start with a product,
[SOUND]
but
can you think of a company that has a lot
of products?
>> Under Armour.
>> Under Armour has a lot of products.
So with Under Armour they're selling,
what?
What does Under Armour producer sell?
>> T-shirts.
>> Shirts.
>> Shorts.
>> Shoes.
>> Socks.
>> sports equipment.
>> Sports equipment like.
>> Equipment, baseball.
>> Okay, so baseball equipment.
Lacross equipment.
>> Underwear.
>> Backpacks.
>> Hats.
>> Headbands.
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Sweatshirts.
>> String bags.
>> Training bags.
>> Socks.
>> Okay we already had socks.
>> Water bottles.
And they sell, again, cleats.
They sell, coats.
Jackets.
What did they start selling?
What was product number one?
A shirt much like you're wearing.
Want to stand up?
Yeah.
So, a
shirt.
A shirt.
Are you going to get investors excited
about selling a shirt?
No.
Are investors going to take you seriously
if you come in
and say well, we want to launch 30
different products this week.
>>
>> No.
So you kind of have to find
the balance of, let's focus on step one,
of what are we going to do first,
and it's often doing one product well, and
we might not be able to sell a black.
It's called hereford?
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> So we might not be able to sell
a black hereford basketball shirt, what
size is that?
>> it's a large.
>> In large, and that be our only
product.
What's the problem with that.
>> Market size.
>> Your market size might be 40 people.
So again with apparel, it's a little bit
tricky
and you might need different colors and
you might
need different sizes, but you want to
recognize, we
need to start relatively small to have
some success.
And to turn a little bit of money into
more
money that we can then invest into the
next thing.
But also recognize that when you think
about service and product
lines, you're probably not going to be
just a shirt company forever.
You're probably going to expand and grow
that into other areas.
So, that's something to think about as
well.
>> Under Armour makes, like, the unique
shirt that's pure nylon.
Hasn't really been done before.
How did they find a manufacturer?
>> Well, there are a couple of embedded
questions.
One, you know, what they've done, and has
it
been done before, and were other people
doing it?
You know, is a question but a more
fundamental question is, how do you find
your manufacturers?
And you can go online, you can go to the
Ali Babas and the Thomson registries, you
can Google and try
and find, you can go to, you know, other
small
companies, maybe outside of your region
and see who they're using.
You can do those things but in time, who
do you think Under Armour wanted to make
their stuff?
When they got to the point that they were
getting some momentum and they needed to
find the company by name that they wanted
to partner with to make their stuff.
Who else do you think that company made
stuff for?
>> Nike.
So they wanted to know in time, who makes
Nike stuff?
And so they found that
person and then they went to China and met
with him.
Why did that make sense?
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Go ahead.
>> Because they know what they're doing?
>> Because you want somebody that's a
leader.
You want somebody that's been there,
that's done
it, that knows it, that can do it.
Now you might also have a little bit of
reservation.
Well do I want my biggest competitor's,
supplier
to be my supplier too, and how am I
concerned about crossover in knowledge and
confidentiality and so
there was this, some elements to work out
but
fundamentally, when you're looking at
service and product
lines, the lesson here is recognized, you
might start
with one or two things, but it's hard to
build a sizable company just doing that
one thing.
So think about, how do we extend?
How do we grow?
What makes sense for future products that
we could launch, that are favorable.
So for Under Armour to go from shirts, to
pants,
to jackets, to hats, to shoes, to
equipment, you see there's some rationale
to it.
But should they have gone into making
iPhone cases?
>> No.
>> Could.
There's a brand.
So why don't they spend a lot of time on
figuring out how to make iPhone cases?
>> Because they're mainly just an
apparel company.
>> They are not really known for that.
It's arguably a different customer, it's
arguably different retailer.
I don't go to Dick's Sporting Goods and
Sports Authority looking for iPhone cases.
I look for sporting, apparel and
equipment.
So in that way,
we think about how we can grow and expand
and do it in a way, that makes sense, that
might leverage the customers that we
already have, that
might leverage the relationships and
partnerships that we already have.
Also within this, you want to clarify any
existing or planned intellectual property
that you have.
Any copyrights or trademarks on your
names, your logos,
any patents that you have or that have
filed for,
you will cover them here as well.
For the funding requests.
>>
[COUGH].
>> What you see regarding the trajectory
of finance for most companies, is that
they operate in a model whereby over
time, they're going to have a funding
pattern that
may look something like this.
So in that way, what you see,
[SOUND]
is that over time, my cash flow,
is going to look something like this.
This is time zero.
What do you think this time is?
>> Break even.
What happens at break even?
What's break even?
>> You make the amount of money that you
originally invested.
>> Essentially.
You were close, but not quite there.
Its not that you make the amount that you
originally invested, but you make the
amount per month.
>> That's all of your expenses.
>> That you spend per month.
So in that way, what we essentially mean,
is that revenues equals expenses.
So in that way, based on money made
that month, we can cover expenses from
that month.
Everything that's here, are essentially
losses to date.
Everything that's here, is going to
typically be profits.
So how much money do you need?
How much money do you need to start your
company,
based on this graph?
>> More than you think.
What area of the graph illustrates how
much money you need to start your firm?
>> The part under.
>> The start under the curve.
So in this area, if you know how much
this is, that's how much money you need to
raise.
Make sense?
So that's what
the funding requests are going to be
geared towards.
So with a funding request, it should
specify, how much do we need?
Now, in our example here, it was how much
do we need to break even?
And for your firm, that might be the
amount you ask for initially.
That might be more than you're able to
effectively raise
initially, so you might have to raise it
in stages.
And again, we'll talk about financing a
little bit later and
what that means when you're doing kind of
phases of fundraising.
But fundamentally, you often need some
degree of money.
And maybe it's money that you have as the
founders of the management team.
Maybe it's money you need to get
from elsewhere, but you also want to talk
about where we're going to use it, and
what's the expected income and result of
that, and that's what the income
statements address.
And income statements you're looking at,
what are we going to sell?
At what price?
And, what expenses do we occur?
And what's the profitability thereafter?
so fairly simple in logic and we'll take a
look at that as well.
balance sheets and cash flow statements
are more accounting
instruments, but are helpful in
reconciling where's the money?
Where are our assets?
Where are our liabilities?
And then with cash flow that's very much
like a checking account.
And what money's coming in and what
money's going out.
And other things you, you may include,
come
within an appendix, that are a bit more
about
the team, a bit more about the company,
any
letters of reference, any perspective
customers you've met with.
If you have a letter from a perspective
customer for a product that you've not yet
made
because it says they will buy it, and they
would pay x, amount if it were available.
What's that do for your ability to raise
money?
>> You know that if you make that you're
going to get back a certain amount of
money.
>> You get some degree of confidence,
that
if you'll make it, then they will buy it.
And so in that way, it removes part of the
element of investors wondering
if anybody wants it, of lenders wondering
if you're ever going to make any money.
If you can go through and if you can show,
I've spoken with people, they want it.
They're willing to pay for it,
here's who I've spoken to, here's what
they've said.
So you can include those types of things
within the plan as well.
[COUGH]
So I also want to share the suggested
format from Sequoia Capital,
which is a large venture capital firm in
the Silicon Valley area.
And when you look at Sequoia, they have
invested,
in many companies that you, so when you
look at Sequoia
and some other companies they've invested
in, we see a few here.
Atari.
You know Cypress.
You may know Cisco.
You may know Electronic Arts.
Drop Box.
Evernote.
Nvidia.
Oracle,
Pure Digital.
We're actually going to talk about them a
little bit later.
So you see, perhaps a lot of tech firms
you
don't know but also a lot that you do
know.
[SOUND]
>> Bless you.
>> Thank you.
>> A lot of the mobile ones are still
probably fairly small.
Let's look at the, the web ones.
[CROSSTALK]
>> So Air B and B, if
you know them.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Google, you heard of them?
>>
[CROSSTALK].
>> Game Fly, Instagram.
>>
[CROSSTALK]
Tumblr.
>> TruLu, Tumblr, Youtube, Yahoo, so
they've done alright.
So we'll take a step back here.
So again, Sequoia
invested in the Google's, the Yahoo's, the
YouTubes,
nVidias, Electronic Arts, Tumblr,
Instagram.
So a lot of companies you may know, and
their format is similar and
that they look for that company purpose in
a sentence, typically.
How do you tell somebody what you do in a
sentence?
You have a 500 words sentence
or a one pretty good sentence.
You talk about the problem, here's the
opportunity, here's what it is
we're solving, here's why you should care
about the rest of our plan.
And I like that a lot.
I'm of the mindset if people aren't
convinced that there's
a problem, if people don't see the
opportunity,
they don't care how you're going to solve
it.
Easy to write a business plan, somewhat
formulaic, very easy to write a business
plan.
Harder to find a real problem, harder to
find a good opportunity.
And so I think addressing that and making
that convincing in the beginning, is
important and helpful.
Then there's the question of, how are we
going to solve it?
So instead of coming out of the gate and
saying here's our solution,
[SOUND]
convince me that there's a problem of
opportunity
and then tell me how you're going to solve
it.
And why is now a good time?
What else is going on in the market?
What else has been tried?
What are other people doing or trying to
do or
might do and how is what you're going to
do better?
Are there enough people that care?
If you have a problem, that's
a problem for one person, that's okay.
But unless they're going to pay you,
exceedingly well and unless you're 100%
confident that they're going to say
yes, that's not going to be a market size
worth going after, typically.
So in that sense what we want to do here
is define,
how big's the market, what constitutes
them, competitors again, be careful with
competitors.
Sometimes, particularly with
presentations, people
want to put up a competitor slide
and show five logos and then go to the
next slide.
What's the problem with that?
[SOUND]
>> Is it, people may think you're
advocating for your competitor?
>> Okay, maybe you're advertising, but
if you're supposed to be telling me
about your competition, and you show me
five logos, what have you done?
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
competition.
>> You haven't told me anything.
You haven't told me anything about what do
they do.
How do they do it?
How are you different or better?
So in that way again, talking about the
competitors and
doing some analysis, ideally beyond just
what's on their website.
Again, everybody knows what's on their
website.
You'll want to do some research and do
some investigation beyond that.
And then you begin
talking about your product and you not
only
are describing it in words, but you're
showing pictures.
And even with a written plan, or a
presentation
showing a sketch, showing a rendering,
showing a picture.
If you have the opportunity to show
something tangible or bring something
to a presentation, that's a lot more
significant, that's a lot more meaningful.
It helps people visualize what the
opportunity is, and it also
helps people remember what it is that they
saw.
Business model of how do the pieces
fit, what's the values, what's the
customer segment?
What are the partnerships and alliances?
So how does it work?
What's your price?
Team and the financials.
So you'll see between the two formats, the
SBA element is very detailed,
and a lot of that is often times geared
towards getting a loan from a bank.
The Sequoia Capital one is a bit more
accelerated.
I would argue, a bit more purposeful.
And in that way, for me, I tend to favor
the Sequoia one a bit.
But I like the SBA one and that it gives
you a little bit of
a, deeper lever of insight a deeper level
of detail of the types of things that
you want to be mindful of, and that you
want to address.
In summary, when you think about authoring
the plan, certainly make
sure that you consider the preferred
format for your target audience.
Also, be sure to be clear, specific, and
convincing.
So in that way, beware of these common
mistakes.
Don't make it overly long.
don't make it confusing.
don't try to be overly clever.
but again, focus that you understand the
market, you understand
your customer, that you've got the right
team, and that
you have a clear path for how the business
is
going to grow and how the business is
going to have success.