Today we're going to introduce the
business plan.
And it all starts with defining the
Key elements that we're going to talk
about is.
What is the plan?
Why write a plan?
As well as what are some of the
advantages and disadvantages of authoring
great business plans?
Its essentially your play book for running
the company.
So in that way we're looking at it's a
plan for the creation of the
company, what's it going to take to get a
launched
as well as what's it going to take to
manage it.
And with most plans you're going to be
looking somewhat in a
infinite timeline, what do you think the
business is going to be doing.
Three years from now, five year, five
years from now and in perpetuity.
Now the bulk of your attention and the
bulk of your
pages, and the bulk of your focus is on
what are we
going to do now and what are we going to
do in the next few years?
But it's talking about the marketing,
inclusive of the product design and
development.
It's talking about the operations.
It's talking about the financing, it's
talking about the teams and the
partnerships.
And you're doing it all in typically less
than 20 pages.
So in that way, you could spend hundreds
and arguably thousands of pages on these
topics.
because it's a big deal to write what is
my company going to do.
In every detail forever.
Why is it constrained?
Why is it
often less than twenty pages?
Yep?
>> Potential investors can read through
it quickly.
>> There's the element of well who's the
audience?
And we'll talk about audience.
And the you is the team that's the
audience, or
partners, or investors, or lenders that
may be the audience.
Their attention span is relatively brief.
And even 20 is a bit on the long side.
But in that way if they're going to put
thousands, or
hundreds of thousands, or millions of
dollars into a venture
they want to see the details.
And so that's, again.
While we work with something that I will
call,
kind of a medium weight at this 20 page
element.
As far as, what is it?
So, in that context, it's defining exactly
how
the company's going to materialize,
exactly the market size.
Exactly the competitors.
Why the team have constituted.
And as it plans
to evolve.
Among the founders, the management, and
the advisers and
investors is the right team that can carry
this off.
And its also an owner's manual for the
company.
Even if you don't plan to raise money from
investors, even if you don't plan to seek
a bank
loan, I would argue that a business plan
is
certainly worth doing because it gives you
as the owner.
Some insights and I put some ideas to
paper, and it lets you connect
the dots of how does the project connect
to
the market, connect to the competition,
connect to the financials.
And you can use it as a goal-setting
instrument as well that we'll talk about.
So in that way again, forces you to write
things down, particularly if you're
working as a team.
It helps you to set some goals, it helps
you
to define where do we want to be in a
year.
Where do we want to be in three years,
particularly on the financials,
also helps focus you on what you should do
and what you shouldn't do.
When is it valuable to know what types of
products and services you should do?
Or what types of marketing or customers
you should go after,
after you write the plan initially.
When is it valuable to check in on those
things?
Yep?
>> before you make a new product.
>> Okay.
Before you make a new product, so you may
be very clear in the beginning.
This is what we want to do, this is our
product, this is our audience.
This is how it's competitive.
But in six months, in a year.
What changes?
What changes for your venture a year after
you've started?
Does anything change?
>> The market might change.
Customer's opinions might change.
>> The short answer is, everything may
change.
The market may change, competitors may
Customer needs and wants change.
People know what a netbook is?
Heard of a netbook?
>> Yeah.
>> What's a netbook?
>> A little laptop.
>> A netbook is a laptop?
>> No, a small laptop.
>> A small laptop.
What can you do on a netbook?
Different than a laptop.
>> Bring it around easier.
>> Okay, its highly portable.
Smaller than a laptop, lighter.
What else do you think a netbook was
designed for?
>> Wasn't it designed mainly to use the
internet?
>> The internet.
So again, the name kind of alludes to a
netbook for an internet.
And so, a couple of years ago, people
thought
that everybody was going to replace
laptops with netbooks.
All you needed to do was get to internet,
and you would no longer need a laptop.
You don't need software on your computer.
You don't need files on your computer.
You just need internet access.
And everything is going to be at your
disposal.
And you can buy that net book for half, or
a third,
or a quarter of the price of what a laptop
would be.
But they
never really took off.
kind of died out, why do you think the
netbook market never really took off?
>> Part of it could have been the
popularity of tablets.
>> Okay.
>> So tablets came along and I no longer
really needed a keyboard.
Portable was good, but I'd rather have
more portable.
And kind of the form and the feature and
the function of it.
Was somewhat inferior to tablets pending
your purpose and use of the tablet.
What else do people do?
Anybody not store any files locally?
You just put everything up on Google, you
put everything on these cloud drives, on
Amazon.
You don't keep any files locally at all,
none.
One?
Yes, two, why?
>> My computer shut down so I can't see
this stuff anymore, so I have to do that.
>> Okay so you have some computer
issues, some software issues, or hardware
issues so you can't save files, so you
have to store them online.
So is that your plan?
You're going to do this forever?
>> No, I'm going to get a new one.
>> Okay, so it's kind of a temporary
fix.
You do it?
>> Yeah.
>> Why?
>> Because the computer I use has no
files.
>> Okay, so it gives you a little more
flexibility.
If I don't need my computer with me.
If I'm at work, if I'm at school, if I'm
at library, if I'm with friends, etc.
All I need is Web, and I can get to the
files I want.
What's the problem with that?
What's the downside with that when you go
into a scenario where everything
is online?
What's the problem?
Why only one person doing it
intentionally,
one person does it as an IT workaround.
Why do the other 33 of you store files
locally?
>> It's less convenient.
>> Which is less convenient?
>> Storing them online.
>> Okay, online feels less convenient.
Why?
>> because you have to go on to the
Internet.
>> Because you have to get online we may
not have web access everywhere we go.
So we have to get online, and even if we
do
have web access we have to kind of take
the time.
Yep?
>> It's because I always know if a
websites crashing, or sometimes.
>> Okay.
Sometimes you can't get online.
Sometimes you don't have an internet
connection.
Sometimes sites are unavailable.
Or crash
[NOISE]
why else?
Why not keep your files elsewhere and
remove them from your local PC?
What may happen.
Yep?
>> Well, you, you could be hacked
potentially
[CROSSTALK].
>> Okay.
It's a, people have security issues of
would they potentially be hacked.
Can somebody get on that server and see
those files that are often some
cloud whereas do I have more confidence
that if at least they're on my.
Local if they're on my hard drive, if
they're on
my local device, do I have more confidence
that they're secure?
So again there were a number of reasons
that it never
really took off and it changed and you saw
companies recognize that.
The smart companies
recognized that.
And get out of the netbook market pretty
quickly, and go back into an ultrabook
market which kind sat in between in the
context of still light, still very
portable, but still retained all those
kind of laptop advantages in large part.
What we also saw was a technology that
emerged, hard-drives are increasingly rare
in your laptop.
Why is that the case?
Why have a hard-drive meaning that a disc
that's going
to spin around like a record player to
read data?
Why are they scarce?
>> They easily overheat.
>> There's a heating issue.
>> Solid state drives have replaced
them.
>> What's a solid state drive?
>> Has no moving parts.
>> Okay.
So what we're finding is that the small
these types of things, these solid state
drives that people have had on key rings
and whatnot for a little while now.
That has no moving parts.
It's just kind of data,
you're just getting elements like this
that are big, that are in your laptop.
What's that do for your battery?
You don't have to power anything that
moves?
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
[COUGH]
lasts a lot longer.
>> Your battery lasts a lot longer.
What's that do for your durability?
I can drop this thing and I have no
concern.
That my data broke.
That my drive is not available.
Why?
>> because, like the, the hard drive
where it's spinning
like, since there's small parts, fragile,
and it can break and.
>> Small parts.
So if you have
your lap.
Who has a laptop?
Okay.
A hard drive?
You have a hard drive?
Yeah, so you'll hold it up and drop it and
you'll be okay?
No, now our friend with the solid drive
might not want to
do it, his screen might
break, but different technology, different
durability.
And you don't have the other typical
failures that you
would have when you're working with a
device just from
wear and tear.
So again, different markets, things
change.
Technologies emerge, operations emerge,
and what you see in this
context is that business plans would need
to change as well.
What we see too is that when you have a
plan
it gives you some insight and some ability
to adapt in time.
And in that way as the markets change as
things evolve.
It gives
you a plan for what are we going to do
about that?
It also is very helpful as a communication
tool.
So in that context, it lets you know.
As we're talking with our founders, as
we're talking with prospective investors,
as we're talking with other partners.
What is it we want to say?
How do we want to say it?
How do we all get on the same
page to tell people collectively what
we're going to do,
how we're going to do it, where we're
going to do it,
when we're going to do it, what number is
tied to that?
And so the business plan is where all of
that is sourced from.
Often, business plans required of banks,
required of investors,
why does that make sense?
Why do they want to see your plan?
Yep?
>> They want to know if their investment
work out.
>> They want to know the future.
They want to know what are you going to do
with my money.
And so in that way this is your,
essentially contract of what
you think is going to happen based on the
monies that they're putting in.
And so the plan also will define what is
it we're going to do.
Now when you look at a company they do
lots of things.
Working from the top there's some
organization some
firms, some employees, some or charts,
some structure.
And then you move down and the technology,
they design things oftentimes.
They may procure or buy things, and then
when you go to
the bottom left, and begin to work across,
we may build things we
may manufacture things we may sell and
service things.
And we reap some level of profit in the
end.
Do you know of a company that does all of
this?
Let's go down the route, so Under Armor
shirt, what's Under Armor do?
Based on what's on this chart.
Taking it from the top.
Do they have a firm infrastructure, is
there a company?
>> Yes.
>> There's a company, there's HR, do
they do technology development?
>> Yes.
>> They do.
So they do a lot of these top-line
elements.
What about in the lower left?
These logistics operations.
Do they make
anything?
They make nothing.
Nike makes nothing.
Adidas, Reebok make nothing.
Why is that a true statement?
>> It is outsourced.
What if Nike need to own a golf club
manufacturing facility?
Why would you want to own a golf club
When do people buy golf clubs?
Or track shoes,
or Tennis shoes, made for Tennis.
Yep.
>> When do we need such things?
>> When they're in season?
>> When they're in season.
A lot of people by these type of things in
the Spring.
If you're going to buy snowboard related
things,
you're going to buy it late Fall, early
Winter.
If you're going to buy swim gear you're
going to buy it typically late Spring.
Now it varies a little bit regionally.
Weather patterns, parts of the world, etc.
But for most of these firms they don't
want to own factories.
When they're only using a piece of that
production.
You also hear elements of low cost of
manufacturing.
What happens when I buy a plant and a
location,
and I think that there's a low cost of
manufacturing, a low cost of labor
associated with that?
What happens as communities and markets
and cities grow?
What happens to the cost of labor?
>> It goes up.
So as cities emerge and grow and get more
populous, cost of living goes up.
Cost of labor goes up.
What does that mean if you own that
factory?
Yep?
>> It costs more money, to pay the
workers more.
>> Okay, so in that way all of your
costs went up.
What does it mean if you have outsourced
to that factory?
What do you do?
What do many companies do?
Yep.
>> I mean, it depends on if they have a
long term contract.
>> And if they don't?
>> If they don't, they might leave or
negotiate.
>> You move somewhere else.
You find new providers.
So you see a whole pattern of this
emerging.
And fundamentally, Nike is not the best at
manufacturing.
Under Armor is not the best at
They want to go to the people that know
how to manufacture well.
And they can move around.
Based on who gets better, and who gets
stronger, and who gets more competitive.
Most companies do these elements that are
shaded.
Most companies, there's some element of
company, there's some
element of design, development.
But most firms are not involved in
manufacturing.
Not all firms are even involved in
marketing and selling.
Now, a couple are.
There are a few Nike stores.
There are a few Under Armour stores.
But I would expect that 95 to, probably
99% of what
they sell, is not out of the few stores
that they own.
They're selling into all of the other
retailers.
The big box retailers.
So in that way, even marketing sales they
do, but it may not
be to the in consumer, it might be to some
intermediary as well.
The reason that this chart is helpful is
that you want to think about these.
You want to think about these elements and
value chain, as you're looking at your
companies.
And recognizing what are we going to do
versus what may still need
to be done but we're going to do it
through other partnerships or
agreements or outsourcing.
So, great plans
take some time.
And I've worked with entrepreneurs on
plans where they were on version 17 before
they showed it to the first investor.
And took about eight months to write that
plan.
Typically not the thing you write in a
weekend, typically not
the thing you write in a month.
May take some time.
And particularly, with awareness of
business model canvas.
Doing business model canvas, kind of
validating
your plan, getting that customer feedback,
are things you would want to do before you
write the full business plan.
So in that way disadvantages are takes
time, needs to be updated.
Not something you write once, put on a
shelf, and never look at again.
Also something you want to invite some
critical review of.
In that way, who do you want to review
your plan?
Often times, I have students that want to
see an example of a good plan.
Good plans are hard to see.
Why is that the case?
Why don't I have a whole catalog of
great, successful business plans for you
to look at?
Or if you write great plans?
Are you fine with posting those up on the
internet?
No, hopefully not, why not?
>> because then everybody's going to
know all of your plans essentially.
>> Everybody knows your deepest darkest
secrets.
Everybody knows your plan everybody knows
how you're going to attack, and
have success in a given market and we
don't want to share that.
Rightfully so,
so in that way again we don't want
to typically distribute our plan on an
open basis.
So who do we share it with to get the
speed back that we want?
Who do you show your plan to?
People that you know, hopefully.
So some people that are, have some level
of
insights or expertise, that you may know,
might be a
friend, might be a family member, might be
a
former colleague, might be faculty, might
be other people that
you have met or know in some capacity.
Or other people that you meet that have
some trusted reference or affiliation.
But its again, that's a very discerning on
how you do that, and when you do that.
In summary, when you consider the business
plan, many of us think that
its a document again, its only used for
investors or to get loans.
But as a reminder, this is your owner's
manual.
The business plan, in my opinion, is best
used and best leveraged by
the owners of the company and it's really
your playbook for running the company.
It's a tool plan, track and also adapt the
company it's also a tool for raising
capital but more fundamentally I think if
it's
something that you put sufficient time and
resources into.
And revised periodically, it's something
that can be
used by your senior team within your
organization to
make sure you're doing the right thing at
the right time.
And that you really stay on track to what
your goals are.
And if those goals change, if your
techniques, or tactics,
or strategies are modified, you update the
plan from there.
And so that way again it's a living
document.
That's good not only for investors, but
great for your team.
Alone.