In any discussion of partnerships, it's
also very valuable to understand
outsourcing.
As a unique and very viable opportunity
and category or type of partnership.
When we look at outsourcing, it can happen
in a variety of ways.
There are vertical opportunities to engage
with.
There are transferring existing or entire
pieces or business functions to a partner.
There are various types of outsourcing.
It might be contract-based.
It might be business process, or IT.
It might be innovation outsourcing, and
that you are
engaging others to assist in your product
development or design.
So in that way, when we
think about outsourcing, historically it's
been thought
more of manufacturing Or perhaps call
centers
are very, specific in very narrow areas.
But today, there's a global environment
and global
platforms that we'll talk about that are
particularly viable
for new ventures to be able to find
partners and outsource relationships,
in and beyond your country boundaries.
Why do we do it?
One, there might be expertise.
And a lot of firms do this with law, with
accounting.
Why don't we have an attorney or an
accountant full time in every start-up?
>> because you don't really need an
attorney 24.
>> You don't have the need for
a full-time attorney, or a full-time
accountant.
What else don't you have?
>> No money to pay them.
>> You don't have the money.
[SOUND]
You don't have the money to pay someone
full time.
And even if you did, if you don't have the
need, that money's probably better spent
elsewhere, paying for other things.
So again, we outsource quite a bit, even
if we're
just outsourcing it to someone that's down
the street from us.
It's a different skill set, it's a
different expertise.
We outsource manufacturing largely because
of economies of scale We
may not have the money to buy a big
machine.
And even if we did, we probably don't have
the demand to run that machine all the
time.
So let's find people that own and operate
the machines
and buy the amount of time on that that we
need.
And it may only be an hour or two a day.
So yet you're finding people that have
the expertee, expertise, the resources,
the know how.
That we don't.
How you find them, comes in many flavors.
Elance, that's one of the popular, online
outsourcing
matchmaking firms.
And they report to have had 900.
I'm sorry.
$815 million of transactions on their
site, across 91,000 jobs, 91,000
projects of individuals and small
companies
finding one another.
They claim 176,000
programmers.
192,000 writers.
If I need content written for my site.
If I need content written for marketing
materials and brochures.
If I need mobile 20,000 developers and
so in this model
[COUGH].
What you see here.
Is that the 91,000 jobs is actually posted
in the last thirty days.
So it gives you a sense of magnitude And
that there is a lot of matchmaking.
And they feature different people in the
promos.
So we have an Argentinian that's doing
mobile app development.
Why do I find somebody in Argentina, to do
my mobile app development?
When there may be someone right here in
Maryland that can do that.
>> Might be cheaper.
>> Might be a price advantage, there
might be a skill advantage.
I'm looking for something specific or
unique.
There might be a time advantage, of I want
it, this week, this month, then maybe my
local person.
Can't do that.
Maybe I'm trying to target that market.
Maybe I need something that's Spanish
language.
Maybe I need other things that that person
in that
region is going to know better than
somebody that may be local.
Maybe I'm a US firm developing a mobile
app for deployment in Argentina.
So, again, there are lots of different
motives and lots of different reasons.
[SOUND]
Cost is the one that's common.
But there may be other advantages as well.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the fee model, is that when you go in
and when
you look at one of these profiles, then
again if we were
to click on this, and do our search, and
pull someone up,
we would see skill sets, and price points,
and things of that nature.
And what the Elance business models is, is
there's a transaction
fee for projects that are served and
matched on their site.
So they essentially
earn a commission for matchmaking.
>> Why would it be just, like, I mean
you contact the guy outside of the site
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Typically a lot of these elements are
not posting
contact information, so any time you're
doing a business model
where you're matchmaking online and you're
trying to generate revenues
off of that matchmaking, typically you
hold contact information hostage.
Until the payment to you has been
transacted.
>> All right.
>> And with this model, there are
competitors.
ODesk, is the other big one in this space,
and what they're doing is similarly
doing matchmaking.
They report $257 million of earnings.
Based on matches that they've made, that
the average job size is the 4,300.
And right now, they have 1,400 people
working on projects.
And when you see the cities that are
represented and the regions that are
represented It's not all, just in China.
It's not all, just in India.
There's a lot of activity, a lot of
contractors, a
lot of people doing work, in the U.S, for
U.S firms.
And people, again probably vice versa.
People here that are contracting work over
here.
there.
So in that way, again, it happens in
this kind of global marketplace these days
with outsourcing.
And what you see in the level of
definition that you can
draw down into, is you want, perhaps,
somebody that knows software development.
That knows mobile apps specifically.
That has a feedback score of at least 4.5
on a 5.0 scale.
And you get people that are returned, that
fill those elements.
And at present, when I did that, there
were 47 people,
that fit that profile.
And then I can look at those 47 if I
choose, and see.
What they know by way of skills and
programs, what they charge,
what they have done by way of portfolio,
as in
can I go online and look at past work
they've performed.
So why do I have a $35 person, an $80
person, and
a $50 person?
Which one do I go with?
>> Probably the one with the most
experience which is the $80 person.
>> I might go with the person that has a
lot of reviews.
Yep.
>> That with the most hours.
>> I might like hours.
It seems like maybe they've done fewer
projects.
But maybe bigger projects.
So maybe you acquaint that with
experience?
What if I need somebody that knows
OmniGraffle?
I'm not even sure what OmniGraffle is.
How many of those are there.
>> One.
>> There's one.
So there might be a very specific skill
set or need that I have,
that I pay for.
Or I may do what?
What do we do sometimes when we are
resource-constrained?
>>
[UNKNOWN]
>> We go cheap.
So in that way, again, you have lots of
options.
You have lot's of options in this space to
find people you hope are a good match
and it's not uncommon, that you may find a
small piece of your project.
Rather than the whole thing that you're
trying to
outsource, give somebody a piece and see
how they do.
And do they do that well, and if so, if
their responsive, if their, if it's
timely, if it's quality, then you may go
back to them to do the bigger project.
It's not uncommon that you may hire two or
three people to do the same project.
A small project,
or three similar projects.
Why might you break things up into
bite-sized pieces and give it to different
people?
>> Because they needs maybe the pieces
need certain expertises that Okay.
They might be different skill sets, so
it's more than one person can do.
>> So you can see which one is best for
the big job.
>> It also lets you compare.
It lets me, let me run three people at the
same time, and see who runs the best, and
then
I can pick that one to do the part to the
bigger job.
So there's a little bit of kind of an art
and science in how you do
it, but it's important to recognize with
outsourcing
that it comes in lots of different
flavors.
That there's a global market for it, and
with
the Elances and Odesk, and things like
that that are
out there, they're increasingly easier to
find, and affordable
to find, and these, as I searched them, I
think,
in one of the earlier filters.
I may have clicked U.S, I'm seeing if
there's a, a geography notation here.
You can pick regions that you want to
focus in.
Yeah, so all of these are in the U.S. If I
expanded
that into other international areas, a lot
of the rates would drop.
So if for some reason you want to work
with somebody locally, you want the
time advantage.
You want to be able to get on the phone.
You can do that to.
So again, lots of options.
That you have.
So again, many models.
There's the off shoring of let me find
somebody outside of my home country
There is the, kind of the cap development
of let me set up operations elsewhere.
And there are a number of small start up
firms that I'm familiar with that
they have a small office in Maryland, and
then they have a second office in India.
So they're still a small firm.
They may have 50 people here and 50 people
there.
So they have enough work that they want to
hire and build an operation abroad.
[NOISE]
And they've elected to do that in the
different
[UNKNOWN],
particularly if it's software, or
something that
can scale and grow, beyond their, local
market
[NOISE].
And then there are a variety of other
models of
where you can set up and partner with
people locally.
And when JetBlue got started,
they located their call, their call
center, meaning that
if you were to call JetBlue, you want to
talk about.
Travel you're trying to make, you have
some issue with what
you were billed, you have some customer
service request or complaint.
They set up their call center in Salt Lake
City, Utah.
Why do we set up a call center in Utah?
And we're not only going to set it up in
Utah, but we're going to forward the call
to people's individual homes.
So we're going to have predominantly
women.
Working part time, at home, in Utah, is
our call center for Jet Blue Airlines.
Why would you do such a thing?
>> Utah?
>> Utah.
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
reason?
>> It is a religious reason.
>> That's so messed up.
[CROSSTALK]
>> So, in that way, the founder of Jet
Blue, is a Mormon, and
he believed that, he wanted to create a
call center in the US,
and not international, what was the
perception for that?
[INAUDIBLE]
Not racist.
So in that way, why did he want to set up
a call
center in the U.S. and not abroad, as did
many of his competitors?
>> Because America.
What do you think?
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
wants to give it to them.
>> So he wants to keep jobs in the U.S,
he wants to
create economic development in the U.S.
He perceived there'll be a language
advantage.
He wanted the call center to be served by
people that
had English as their first language, and
thought that equaled better service.
He thought too that, I can have a cost
advantage, and that if
I can make the job easy, if you can work
from home, if
you can set your own hours, and if I can
hire you in
a part time capacity, I don't bear the
cost of full time people.
When do people call their lines?
When do you think most people are calling?
>> They might be bored.
>> They're calling at night.
They're calling weekend.
Business travelers may call during the
day, but
a lot of people are calling off hours.
So in that way too, would he perceive that
for the population
that he was employing There was an
interest in working part time,
that there was an interest in working from
home.
And in that way it was a model that made
sense.
Now as they have grown, as they've
expanded,
they've gone beyond what that market can
serve.
But it was an element of creative home
showing if you will, if you thought that.
Based on, the model, based on the needs.
Now, you cannot require, legally.
You cannot require that
someone be of a certain religion, to be
employable by your company.
But you can certainly locate, and market.
If you're trying to target a certain
Employee that has certain interests.
[COUGH].
But he had a pretty creative solution to
find employees that paralleled the needs
that he had.
We see people specialize.
So when you go to the Elance and you go to
the oDesk, a lot of
it's technology but it's a lot of writing
and creative and it's a whole assortment
of things.
There are some sites that started, and
many
that have still maintaining, doing but one
thing.
And there were a number of logo design
sites that launched Not
too long ago.
And they would offer a fixed fee model,
this model 295, to develop a logo.
It's that expensive.
$295 for a logo.
How do you know if it's expensive?
[CROSSTALK]
>> It's based on competition.
It's based on well, what are my other
options for a logo?
If I hire a designer.
If I go to a marketing agency.
If I go to an ad agency and pay them for a
logo, that could be two or 3,000 dollars.
Now I could have my kid do something in
powerpoint.
For free and I get my money's worth.
But there's an element
of thinking about
what my options are, and again a, an
interesting option at 295.
What's more interesting is that they run
it as a competition model
[COUGH],
meaning that I specify I, am opening, a
salon.
I, am serving this type of customer.
I'm selling this type of product, at this
kind of price point.
I like red.
So, you can give some parameters of what
it is you would like to see in your logo.
You post that.
And then if you have five logo designers
that are members of the sight,
they can elect to create one or more logos
based on the specs that I've created for
them.
And if I choose one as the winner, if I
choose
yours as the winner, you get the $295,
minus a few percent.
That 99 designs keeps.
What do the other four get?
>> Nothing.
It's a competition.
Why do five people design when there's
going to be but one winner?
>>
[COUGH]
>> Try and
[INAUDIBLE]
>> They want to be the winner.
They want to be the winner.
So you see these other competition type
sites That have emerged.
Now someone probably isn't going to design
a whole website.
Somebody's probably not going to invest
weeks of time,
in a competition model.
But for a logo, how long does it take to
make one of these logos?
>> Couple hours.
Couple hours, yeah.
>> Probably a couple of hours if you
were in the business of being a logo
designer.
At least as a version that you can
promote,
and then if somebody wants to change a
little something
with it, you've got the opportunity to
tweak it a
bit, but it's not days and days of time,
typically.
You can also pay more than 295.
295 may be the minimum.
I can offer 495 for my logo.
What does that do?
>>
[INAUDIBLE]
>> You don't get five, you get ten.
Each of those don't submit two logos, they
may submit three of four each.
So again, it's somewhat of a, auction
model, so to speak, of that the more
you pay, the more interest you're going to
get, and the more options you may have.
And you choose the winner, and or, you
have a little
link that you can send out to friends and
colleagues and
family, and have them vote on what they
like too.
So in that way you can do some voting to
help you determine what you want to pick.
But again, different model of outsourcing,
kind of competition based.
So with outsourcing again, as we've talked
about, you can
save some money, you can focus on what you
do well.
And find other people that do what they do
well.
You also might be able to access people
you
otherwise couldn't find, or get skills you
otherwise wouldn't have.
Also it costs money to hire people.
Even if you're going to pay somebody
$30,000 a
year, you're pending the size of your
company.
Are really going to be paying more like
$40,000.
So
how does a $30,000 salary cost you
$40,000?
Where's the other ten go to?
>> Benefits.
Healthcare.
Taxes.
Employment taxes.
If you want them to come to work you have
to have space for them to
sit in and equipment for them to use and
furniture for them to have access to.
So there's a lot of other added costs.
So you again, by partnerting with people
that do that and can do that elsewhere.
And or do it part time from home, there
might be other cost savings there as well.
There are some risks involved.
Doesn't always work out.
The logos you get aren't always the ones
you want.
The app that somebody built may not be
the app that you thought they were
going to deliver.
So there's again, an awareness of that.
And that's why, with many of these things,
you typically, you typically in
the beginning, with people you're
unfamiliar with,
have small projects at small amounts of
money, and then you can kind of grow and
scale it from there.
What a lot of these sites to, as well with
the Elances and the oDesk, how do you know
if work is being done, on your software
development?
Now if your going to check in with them,
once a week.
And by voice.
How do you know that work is being done in
the interim?
Particularly if your paying them by the
hour?
[NOISE]
You do.
How do you know?
>> You can do desktop sharing.
>> Okay, you can do desktop sharing and
you
can stay awake all the time, and kind of
watch them.
I'm going to watch you do work.
What's a little bit better than that?
>> I know I use progress reports when I
do stuff like that.
>> So there's some progress reports.
What else might they do?
>> Well, oDesk has it all built in
where,
if you're paying somebody on oDesk, you
get a like, report.
You can see their screen like every ten
minutes, and it breaks down their screen
into like what programs they're using and
you get to see a chart of that.
>> So, you essentially have installed
spyware.
They're taking screenshots.
Every few minutes.
Where you can go in and get a report of
what's happened in the last hour, week,
month, what have you.
However long they've been working with you
as related to your project.
How do you know if you're working at a
company, if you ask
an employee to do something, are they
working on it during that day?
Particularly in this cube environment that
we have,
how do you know if they're doing anything?
Not in the same way.
Of the, we'd be up in arms in the U.S. if
their privacy has been invaded at work.
Yeah.
>> Can you check on them?
>> You can keep checking.
>> Do we want to be checked on every
three minutes by our boss?
[CROSSTALK]
It's awkward.
You would, could argue, that with the
Elance and the oDesk
and some of the technology that they use
and have and
that people volunteer to engage in, gives
you better oversight than
we have of our own employees that work in
our own office.
But it's being aware again of what's out
there.
>> The last person that voted for
Leedan, do you know who that is?
>> we'll do it in a minute.
so with that way for the outsourcing, what
you want to recognize, is that it happens
in lots of models and it happens in lots
of ways and it doesn't always work out.
You know, there's risk in any kind of
partnership.
there's risks in any kind of relationship.
We also want to recognize to what extent
can you change your mind.
Can what extent can you drop off with one
person and start with another person if
need be?
If a person building that app isn't
working out,
are you starting from scratch with the
next person?
And has what money you paid kind of gone?
Or have they built a piece that I can use
that piece in the next piece?
So that's why again breaking things into
small projects typically works well.
There are also can be backlash to what you
do.
When you're thinking about outsourcing.
When you're thinking about outsourcing, or
if to outsource.
These are a few critical questions to
consider.
One I would look at is the criticality of
the business function.
If you're a technology company.
If you're a web based company.
If people are paying to use, and interact
with your software and your web.
I would probably say you don't
want to outsource your website.
You probably need to find people to join
your team that
are in the business of doing that and
doing it well.
If you sell socks and you're in the
business of making
socks, it may make a lot of sense to out
source your website.
That's all you need is something that
looks good, that's kind of brochureware
of what it is.
Maybe you want to have a shopping cart on
your site.
Like the basis of your success, it's not
on how
good your shopping cart is or how good
your site is.
It's the product itself.
So in that way again, it depends on what
you're doing,
and it depends on the criticality of that
to your business.
And that's what this is oriented towards
of how mission critical is it?
If it goes down can
you fix it?
If it doesn't work, is, are you going to
lose customers because of it?
And if the answer's yes, you probably want
to do that
skill and do that resource by the members
of your team.
If it's things that are somewhat
interchangeable, if
it's things that are not necessarily
mission critical,
If it's something you need infrequently,
then you
may very well outsource that with some
frequency.
When you think about the nature of the
process,
there's also the question of being able to
recognize.
Is it hard?
Or is it easy to tell somebody what it is?
If you have something
that's relatively simple to explain,
that's relatively specific in what and how
you need it done, and it's not necessarily
time critical,
that's something that you can hire someone
to do.
That's something that you may very well
outsource very effectively.
If it is complex, if there's a lot
of customization to it, if it's hard to
describe
it, and kind of hard to do it, that maybe
the type of thing that you do in house.
There's the kind of the transfer of it,
related to, somewhat the complexity
I think these go hand in hand a bit of can
you explain what it is you want?
Can you quantify it?
Can you measure it?
Can you validate it?
Sales is something that you could argu,
arguably measure
pretty well, and you can hire an outside
sales team.
And if they sell, they get compensated.
If they don't, they don't.
So it's a clean line of impact or
effectiveness.
There's also the element of the
intellectual property
piece of who owns what, and/or what
happens
if somebody breaks that and runs off with
your patents or with your copyrights or
trademarks.
There's one case of an individual that
made
disposable diapers, no not disposable,
reusable diapers.
Reusable diapers, and her model is that
there
is a cloth diaper with snaps, that's on
the
exterior and there is a secondary layer of
cloth, that goes on the interior.
So if you need to change the diaper, you
unsnap,
then you take the interior part,
dump it if it needs to be dumped.
Otherwise, you put it in to be laundered
later that day, and you replace that
little interior
piece, it's an insole almost and you snap
that diaper back up and you're off and
running.
[NOISE]
What do people spend on diapers?
>> I don't know.
>> A lot.
>> I have no idea.
>> It accumulates over time.
It's thousands of dollars per baby.
You might think it's gross to change a
diaper.
That's true if it's a disposable diaper or
if it's a, reusable diaper.
So in that way again the people that are
buying these are concerned about,
is that gross or not?
That comes with the baby.
But what she did, is she found a provider
abroad and before she got her
product I just sold into the market,
she had competitors selling the exact same
thing.
So it does happen.
[SOUND]
It does happen.
That if you outsource things, the folks
you are
not familiar with, even if you have a
patent.
[COUGH]
All patents do is give you the right or
the beginning, of what you need with a
lawsuit.
You still need to litigate that and
typically hire attorneys to litigate that.
So, it's something to be aware of.
It's something to be cautious of.
Particularly too, with fashion and
apparel, hard to get patents that stick,
because we can just add a third button.
We can make it an inch longer.
It's fuchsia instead of pink.
So again, it's subtle differences.
So it may give people the opportunity to
work around patents.
We also recognize the inventor capability.
So what do people know?
What can they accomplish and do they have
the right skills?
And that's where references come in as
well.
Governance, we talked about that a little
bit.
That's more the contract element.
In summary, when you think about
outsourcing, there are rich
and valuable avenues for new ventures to
engage in this.
And the outsourcing opportunities, and the
outsourcing
jobs and roles are widely diverse, and
they exist in many forms.
So we can encourage you to think about
that, to think about how you can add value
to your customers, and add value to your
company, by finding the right outsourced
relationships and partnerships.
Also think about the risk.
There are inevitably risks when you do
anything with any one else.
But there some best practices as discussed
here
that you can try to mitigate those risks.
That you can think
about how do I select the right partners
in the beginning and then how
do I put a process in place
to manage those outsourced relationships
effectively and effeciently.