Today we're going to discuss sales
forecasting.
And this is something that I see as a
critical challenge for many entrepreneurs.
And it's very difficult to try and make
a reasonable forecast of what are your
sales, what
are your revenues going to be a year from
now, two years from now, three years from
now.
For a product that you haven't built for a
market that you've researched, which
you haven't yet entered, and versus
competitors
that you have not yet competed against.
So in that
way, we'll look at some tools and some
techniques for
how to make these sales forecast for a new
venture.
Fundamentally, we'll talk about what are
some business models
and business plan impacts and how does the
sales forecast
impact your model and your plan and why is
a good sales forecast necessary to have a
convincing plan.
We'll also examine how to forecast these
sales and how
to set some revenue goals.
And we'll work through some, what I
believe to
be novel approaches to that, that help
with understanding
the target profits of your company and
then working
backwards from there, to get to your sales
forecast.
We want to recognize that, again, you're
doing this to plan your
business because based on how much you
think you're going to sell,
it's going to really dictate how you're
going to build the company.
How many people you need, what types of
resources
you need, what your expenses are going to
be as well.
And so the orientation of that is, that
sales is typically the starting point
of building out the rest of your income
statement and the rest of your financials.
We want sales to be high, typically,
because we want
them to be convincing to investors,
convincing to lenders.
But what happens if they're too high?
What happens if we come in and we
say we're going to sell a million this
year, or
5 million this year, or 10 million this
year
and we don't have anything to back it up?
>> so they're not going to believe you?
>> There's an element of feasibility.
There's an element of reality.
if you think you can sell a million, or
you
think you can sell 5 million, and you have
a plan
to get there, and your plan is logical and
rational then you can certainly do that.
But it's important, again, to recognize
that depending on where you're going to
get money from there might be some
expectations of what they have.
Investors are typically looking for big
returns
and so they're looking for pretty rapid
growth.
Banks, somewhere in the middle they want
you
to be able to pay back whatever you lend.
But they don't need you to
necessarily be on the cover of Fortune in
a year.
If it's your money, you can move at
kind of the pace that you want to move at.
So again, the type of financial capital
you have will dictate sales
[UNKNOWN]
as well.
But again, fundamentally, for most
ventures, be
it profit or non-profit, you need to
generate
enough sales to help the company be
successful
and to reach the goals that you have.
So we're going to look at the income
statement
as a tool for how to develop sales
forecasts.
So there are a lot of financial statements
that are
out there and we'll talk about some of
those later.
They're normally the income statement, the
balance sheet, the cash flow statement and
we'll talk about how those fit within
business plans.
But what we see within the income
statement is at the top line, there's
revenue.
What are we going to do in sales?
Typically on a quarterly, or annual basis,
there are cost of goods
sold, which is, in a large part,
manufacturing cost or production cost.
What's it take to produce that individual
unit that we're selling.
There's SG and
A, which is selling, general and
administrative, and a
big piece of that is the marketing and
sales costs.
So, selling cost include marketing as
well.
And when you begin to think about what are
the different pieces of the expenses, you
add those up.
You get some sense of timeline, of what
are we going to spend, for what purpose,
and
that guides you towards the answer of how
much money do you need to start the firm.
Profits or
the result revenues minus expenses, taxes
will be taken out of that as well.
Revenues and sales, again, synonymous
terms,
means the same thing for our purposes.
So that's your price per unit times number
sold.
Expenses come in a few different ways.
There are variable expenses, meaning that
for every unit
of production, I have some cost associated
with that.
There's material costs, there's labor
costs, there's energy costs, so there's
other costs that I incur for every unit
produced or sold.
There are fixed costs, one time costs.
What are a one time cost for a cafe?
What kind of cost am I incurring one time?
>> The coffee machine?
>> I may be buying equipment.
And that equipment might not last forever,
but it's probably
going to last years, or 5 years, or 10
years.
So it's largely one time.
What other one time costs am I incurring?
There's equipment, there's.
>> real estate if you're buying.
>> Okay, if you going to buy the
property, you have
a land cost, a building cost, that's
going to be one time.
If you're going to rent the property, it's
going to be a recurring fixed cost.
You sign your lease, it's $3000 a month,
you pay that each and every month.
If you sell no product, you pay $3000.
If you
sell millions of product, you pay $3000.
So in that way, again, we have fixed costs
that are one time, but they also might be
interval.
What about labor?
What kind of cost is labor?
>> Isn't labor variable?
>> It's variable, so based on how much I
sell,
I'm going to decide how much I'm going to
pay my employees.
Who works, anybody work?
Okay.
What do you make?
>> $9 bucks an hour.
And if you have a busy hour, they pay you
a little more?
>> No.
So is that a variable or fixed?
>> It's fixed.
>> Fixed.
What happens if business is really bad?
What happens next month?
>> I don't have any
[INAUDIBLE].
I would like to think it would stay the
same because.
>> Oh, we would doubt that it would stay
the same.
What's likely to happen?
[CROSSTALK].
You'd probably get scheduled for fewer
hours.
So again, it's kind of fixed but it's kind
of variable, so again, some
things might fit in different categories
and
you might have different types of labor.
You might have salary where people make X
dollars per
year, or X hours per hour, and that's
pretty set.
You might have other people that are
commissioned based.
Particularly sales people are often
commission based.
What's commission?
>> I think
you get extra money on top of your, like,
salary for how much you sell.
>> You make some percentage of your
sale, so you might make 8, 10, $12
an hour, but you might make 3 or 5%
commission in addition to that.
So in that way, again, it's an added
incentive,
and so it's a combination of fixed and
variable costs.
So, again, think about these when you're
thinking
about your venture, and what types of cost
you incur, when, and for what purpose.
What that looks like, and this is just a,
kind of a,
abbreviated income statement, is that you
have your revenues on top, or sales.
For example in year one, we only, only
may have one product or one category of
product.
We have expenses associated with that,
there's some R&D cost, there's some
cost of goods sold, there's some
marketing, there's some salaries, and
there
might be other pieces that are missing
from this.
If you're doing a bricks and mortar, a
face to face retail operation,
you would have lease or rent in there, you
would have utilities in there.
So think about what cost makes sense
for the types of ventures that you're
considering.
And there's going to be a pretax profit.
Just simply revenues minus expenses.
There is taxes, taxes vary widely based
on the type of business you're in, the
country
and the region and the city that you're
operating within.
So again, the 20% here is just an example.
you want to be aware of what the taxes are
wherever you're operating.
After tax is simply profit, minus tax.
And then your net profit margin is that
profit after tax divided by your revenues.
When you look at
year two, our revenues went up.
Why is that a reasonable assumption?
Yep.
>> Your product is more known.
>> Okay, you begin to build a brand.
>> You could also release a second
product.
>> You released a second product, as
what we see here.
>> you're not paying to start things up
again.
>> You aren't paying as much R&D.
And again, and here we don't see a fixture
or facility or other element, but in
practice you may.
so again, you might not have incurred
some of those start-up costs again, but
here we do see R&D is lower.
What is higher?
>> Marketing.
It would make sense that if we take our
marketing budget from $15,000 to $70,000,
that our marketing should be better.
That it should generate more sales.
Oftentimes I see this misrepresented,
where people
think they're going to spend a lot in
marketing
to begin with, and then that's going to
decline
over time and their sales are going to
increase.
Marketing and sales tend to be somewhat
complimentary.
You tend have to put more in marketing to
get more sales.
And to keep sales high you need to put
more in marketing.
So in that way, again, you do benefit from
brand, maybe you benefit from repeat
customers, maybe there
are the partnerships you establish that
contribute to sales.
But be careful not to under-invest in
marketing or try and contract your
marketing.
What about salaries?
We're paying 5K the first year.
Not a very good salary.
>> well you could of given out a raise
or hire more employees.
>> But what are we getting for 5K a year
in year one?
So to give you a sense of what 5K is, if
it's 50 weeks, it's how much a week?
>> 500.
>> Nope.
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> {INAUDIBLE] Have to take a refresher
math course.
>> It's a hundred.
5000 divided by 50, a
hundred a week.
So, most entrepreneurs, you're at a 50, 60
hour
a week, so you're making about 2 bucks an
hour.
>>
[CROSSTALK].
>> Good wage?
>>
[CROSSTALK].
>> And there might be two or three or
four of
you working on it, so you're making about
$0.50 an hour.
>>
[CROSSTALK].
>> You save up all day, you can go to
Starbucks.
You'd probably have to share it with your
team.
Why do we do such things?
>> For the future, because.
>> because we have a future mindset.
So it's not uncommon that there may be few
if any dollars,
particularly for the founders and the
executives of the team, in the beginning.
And you worked largely for free for a
period of time.
And that's typically the norm.
How do you pay your rent?
How do you make your car payment?
How do you eat?
>> Second job.
>> You might work somewhere else.
Hard, in my experience, to start a company
successfully while you're working full
time somewhere else.
So there's an element again, of kind of
how do I manage my time?
Do I work full time somewhere and start my
venture at night and on the weekend?
Do I work part time at night on
the weekend and start my venture during
the day?
What else might you do?
>> Take loans.
>> You might take loans but, again, in
the beginning
it's going to be hard for your venture to
get funding.
And banks want what when they make loans?
>> Interest.
>> Interest in?
>> Future profitability.
>> What do they, when you
get a loan, what do banks typically like?
Starts with a C.
>> Cash.
>> Credit, cash money?
>> Ends with an L.
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Second letter's O.
>> Collateral.
What is collateral?
>> Like your house or your car.
>> Collateral are assets.
I borrow money to buy a house.
I don't pay my mortgage, what happens to
my house?
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Bank owns it.
I borrowed money for a car, I stopped
paying
my car payment, bank comes picks up my
car.
So again, you might be able to get loans
in the beginning but
they're probably going to be personal
loans,
meaning that you have to have collateral.
If you don't have collateral, might be
hard to get a loan.
People heard of savings?
Kind of rare these days.
A lot of entrepreneurs have saved some
money, and
or, just live cheaply to get their
ventures moving.
And that way they can put their full
attention to it.
And take advantage of the opportunities
that they see ahead of them.
So again, this is the starting point for
thinking about sales forecast and
this is kind of what you want to end up
with in the end.
When you're doing your investor
presentations, when
you're doing your business plans, you'd
like
to be able to craft something that kind of
looks like this in the end.
But there's a question of where do you
start?
What numbers do you start putting in
initially?
What's the first number you put in?
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Expenses or revenue?
>> Expenses, but again I don't quite
know what my expenses are.
Maybe I know that I need a location and
maybe that's $3,000 a month.
Maybe I know that I need some equipment
and that's $10,000 a month.
But I don't necessarily know how much
labor I need.
I don't necessarily know much inventory I
need.
So there's
still some gaps.
So where else do you start?
because it is a bit of a puzzle.
What was your, somebody said another?
>> Was it the.
>> Where do you start?
You might start with the revenues.
We like to start in the upper left-hand
corner.
To cling to English system, that's where
we start reading, so we
look to that upper-left and we think that,
that's our starting point.
So what do you put down for your year one
revenues?
When you think about the ventures that
you're going to start?
What's your year one revenue goal?
>> At least break even.
>> At least break even but
you don't know yet what your expenses are.
So you can't
set it to break even without knowing your
expenses, so what's your revenue goal?
[SOUND].
Yep.
>> Manufacturing costs and all the other
costs plus your.
>> But you don't know what your
manufacturing costs are
unless you know what your sales are
going to be, right?
So it's a bit of a chicken and egg.
Yep.
>> It'd be like the money you put
into actually start up, like, the company
or business.
>> You might not have a sense of how
much you need to put in without knowing
your expenses,
which you don't know unless you know your
revenues.
So where do you start?
because you guys are going to be doing
this later today.
What's your starting point?
>> Find out market research.
>> What does that do for you?
>> How many people you're going to sell
to.
It's a bit tricky.
I would argue that you would start on
thinking about the profit and the profit
margin.
How do I know profit margin?
Seems like an odd place to start.
How do I know profit margin for my
business?
How
do you know what the temperature is
outside?
>> {INAUDIBLE].
>> Forecast.
>> You don't forecast it.
What's the temperature outside now?
>>
[INAUDIBLE].
>> How do you know?
>> Look it up.
>> You look it up.
You look it up.
There is significant research out there on
what are the
profit margins on average for various
industries and market sectors.
So again, you look it up, you figure
out what's the average profit margin for
my industry.
Now what do we know about averages?
>> Half
are above.
>> Half are above and half are below.
So for you, if you're in a, operating in a
premium market, you might be a little bit
above that.
If you're a start-up and don't have the
economies of scale of
a lot of companies, you might be a little
bit below that.
But it gives you at least a starting point
of
thinking about what's the average profit
margin in my industry.
If you know profit margin, you can begin
to
get a sense of what your income goals are
and what your profit
needs to be to reach those income goals
and then
you can back out your revenues from there.
And we'll look at how to do that.
Once you have a revenue target in mind,
then you can
figure out what expenses do I incur to
reach that revenue goal.
So again,
start with profit margins and profit
dollars.
From there you can get to revenues, and
from there you can get to expenses.
So how we do that is using this concept
called a
reverse income statement, where you start
with some element of profit.
And for many people their profit, their
year one, their
year two profit is going to be some
element of opportunity cost,
of what is it that you might be foregoing
to start this venture.
And most people would like to at least
have
enough in the end that they could cover
their salaries.
And so if you have a two person team, if
once everything is
said and done and once you've paid all of
your expenses, if you
wanted to be able to take home $50,000
each at the end of
year one, then you would have a year one
profit goal of $100,000.
If the average profit margin in your
industry is 20%,
you need $500,000 in revenue for the 20%
profit of that
to equal the $100,000 that is your goal.
Does
that make sense?
And so, in that way, to know I have this
$500,000,
there's a question of what do I do to get
to that?
How do I reach that?
And so then we go down the path
of incorporating other assumptions and
thinking about the expenses.
Now that 20%, again, how did I get that?
And there are a variety of resources
out there, I have a link here for some
work that the business school in NYU
has put together.
And again this a sample, if you go to
this link you'll see dozens and dozens of
various industries.
Industries listed, but for apparel, for
example, based on the 54 firms
that they surveyed, on the far right-hand
side, you'll see 6.59%
as the average net profit margin for
apparel.
So that could be the number that you would
start
with as you are beginning to think about
your venture.
Now you can flex that, you can add a
little to it, you can subtract
some from it, thinking about where you
operate, but it gives you a starting
point.
And the income statements are a bit of a
puzzle as well,
you begin building it out and somethings
fit and other things don't.
And then you, again, revise and amend some
of
those and add some things, and take some
things out
to get to something that you believe is
realistic and comfortable.
But, the orientation here is that, again,
to pick a revenue goal is somewhat
arbitrary.
To say I want to make a $100,000, I want
to make
a million, I want to make a hundred
million, it's kind of random.
To go through and do expenses, you're just
kind of operating in the dark
without knowing what revenues are we
trying
to achieve, but again, profit people
understand.
Profit as far as, what are we going to
take home as the owners
or the founders of the company, I think is
a little more tangible.
And so, again, when you start with that
profit, you recognize your margin.
You back out what your revenue targets are
from there.
And then you can
figure out what expenses is it going to
take to reach that level of revenue.
So from there, there is the question of,
well once we know
the revenue and profit goals we need to
fill out the expenses.
If you are a new company in a new market
without a lot of other companies to
look at, you really have to think about
well,
what are each line item expense we're
going to incur.
Do we need a facility?
Do we need inventory?
Do we need equipment?
Do we need marketing?
Do we need this and that, and you build
that up incrementally.
If you are working in a space where there
are some existing players, particularly if
they are public companies, you can see
what they spend on a per item basis.
And that gives you some sense of what the
industry norms are as well.
And then you can see, for example in
apparel, if you look at the Gaps and the
others that are out there, and you see
that,
well they spend $400 million a year on
marketing,
is that what you're going to spend in year
one?
No, but if their marketing expense is 30%
of their sales, what can you do when you
know your revenue target?
What's the logical way to use that data?
Who's my apparel folks?
Okay, what do you do with that?
Just start in the middle.
What do you do with that number?
>> Sorry, could you repeat the question?
>> So Gap spends 30% of their sales on
marketing, how much did you spend?
>> Since we're new, I don't think we can
spend more than 30 or probably less, like
10%.
>> 10%.
>> 10.
>> I would argue more.
Why more?
>> I was going to say more because since
we're a
new company and we need to get our name
out.
>> You are new.
People don't know you.
People don't know you're Gap.
People don't know you're Old Navy.
People don't know you're Banana Republic.
Means you might need to spend 35, 40, 45%
of your revenues on marketing.
So in that way, it gives you some sense of
starting point and
what has it taken for industry leaders to
have success in their space.
In summary, when we look at sales
forecast, and we recognize that it is
a first step to being able to
develop reasonable financial statements
for the firm.
Also when you do these sales forecasts, I
would
certainly advise you to think about this
goal setting approach.
Think about
the reverse income statement.
Think about this as a helpful starting
point
for developing sales forecasts that are
real, sales forecasts
that are achievable, and sales forecasts
that will help
you reach the goals for you and your
organization.